An Annotated Calendar of the Letters of Charles Darwin in the Library of the American Philosophical Society 1799-1882 Mss.B.D25
American Philosophical Society
- Non-Carroll Darwin Materials
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell,[bart.], Nov. 10, 1853; 7x4-1/2; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
    A.L.S. 10p. Concerning volcano craters. Refers to von Buch.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, [bart.], Nov. 20, 1853; 7x4-1/2; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
    A.L.S. 16p. Concerning volcanoes.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, [bart.], Nov. 23, 1853; 7x4-1/2; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
    A.L.S. 4p. Concerning volcanoes.
  - Letter to Sir Charles [Lyell, bart.], Nov. 30, 1853; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Conybeare, William Daniel, 1787-1857
  - Letter to Sir Charles [Lyell], [1853] Sunday; 4 1/2" x 7"; Forbes, Edward, 1815-1854
    Sunday A.L.S. 4P. Wide distribution of certain species of mollusca (?).
  - Letter to Sir Cha[rle]s Lyell, [1853] Saturday; 4 1/2" x 7"; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    [ca.] A.L.S. 2p. Promises to send figure of the Gasteropod larvae.
  - Letter to Mrs. [K.M.H.] Lyell, [1853] Saturday Evening; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Edgeworth, Michael Pakenham, 1812-1881
    Saturday. A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see Lyell album, C) Botany. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Sir Cha[rle]s Lyell, [ca. 1853] Saturday; 4 1/2" x 4"; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    Saturday [ca.]. A.L.S. 3p. and enc. - 1p, and il. Larval state of Gasteropod (Doris). Encloses illustration.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, Feb. 18, [1854]; 8" x 10"; Darwin, Charles,1809-1882.
    Down...A.L.S. 4p., add. Printed: Life and letters of C. Darwin, c.1, 390. B D25.L no. 108
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, [bart.], June 20, 1854; 7-1/4x4-1/2; De La Beche, Henry T. (Henry Thomas), 1796-1855
    A.L.S. 4p.and add.,end. Concerning geology.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, June 26, 1854; 4 1/2" x 7"; Forbes, Edward, 1815-1854
    Edinburgh, A.L.S. 4p. and env., end. Spalacotherium. Hard work getting faily lectures into shape; lacks assistance. Has capital class of highly intelligent students. New edition of the manual.
  - Letter to ----, July 29, 1854; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Ehrenberg, Christian Gottfried, 1795-1876
    A.L.S. 1p. In German. (see Lyell album, C) Concerning Horner. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Sir Charles [Lyell], Sept. 17, 1854; 5" x 8"; Forbes, Edward, 1815-1854
    A.L.S. 6p. and env., end. Has been geologising in the highlands. Ramsay on Permian ice-action. Foliation of metamorphic rocks (?).
  - Letter to [Sir Charles Lyell, bart.], Oct. 31, 1854; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Busk, George, 1807-1886
    Greenwich, A.L.S. 6p.and end. Concerning mollusks.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, [bart.], Feb. 13, 1855; 7x4-1/2, 3-1/2x4-1/2; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 10p. Concerning geology and sandstone. Refers to Sedgwick.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir;", 28 Feb., [1855-1861]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    A.L.S. 3p.bordered. Concerning fossils and Strata. Presses publication to fend off "the most spiteful Reviews."
  - Letter to [Arthur Henfrey], March 17, [1855]; Darwin, Charles, 1806-1882.
    Down, Farnborough, Kent, A.L.S. 2p. Interested in a citation from Henfrey's translation of Braun's work.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir;", 21 March, [1855-1861]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    A.L.S. 2p. Forwards niece's article on worms to Gardners' Chronicle. Thanks for good review.
  - Letter to [Arthur Henfrey], March 31, [1855]; Darwin, Charles, 1806-1882.
    Down, Farnborough, Kent, A.L.S. 3p. Thanks for assistance. Braun citation not known to Hooker or Bentham. Mentions Agassiz & Strickland.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, April 9, 1855; 5" x 8"; Fleming, John, 1785-1857
    Leith, A.L.S. 4p. Comments on Lyell's fifth edition of Manuel of elementary geology.
  - Letter to [Charles] Lyell, May 31, 1855; 9x6; Bunbury, Charles James Fox, Sir, 1809-1885
    Berlin, A.L.S. 6p. (see Lyell album, C) Botany. Geology. Mentions Humboldt and Hooker. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, June 6, 1855; 5" x 8"; Fleming, John, 1785-1857
    Leith, A.L.S. 3p. and enc. - 3p. Encloses his remarks on Stigmaria; comments.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, [bart.], London, June 6, 1855; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Berlin, A.L.S. 3p.and add. In French. Seal. Friendly letter. Concerning geology.
  - Addressed envelope to Dr. R. C. Alexander, London, 11 July, 1855; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    A.D. 1p.,end.
  - Letter to [Robert Hunt], July 22, [1855]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    A.L.S. 4p. Thanks for glass specimens. Has read his book on light. Wishes glasses like these and asks what tint is best where he might procure them.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, Aug. 11, 1855; 4 1/2" x 7"; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    Royal College of Surgeons, A.L.S. 2p. Identification of certain fossil species.
  - Letter to Mr. Horner, Sunday Evening [1855-1861]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    Down, Bromley, Kent, Sunday Evening. A.L.S. 1p.on card;end.on reverse. Thanks for memorandum from [G.R.] Lepsius.
  - Letter to [Eliza Meteyard], Thursday [1855]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, [bart], March 5, 1856; 7x4-1/2; Busk, George, 1807-1886
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, March 18, 1856; 4 1/2" x 7"; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    R. College of Surgeons, A.L.S. 3p. and env., end. Identification of specimens. Protest by Waterhouse in re British Museum affairs.
  - Letter to Sir Charles [Lyell, bart.], April 24, 1856; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Jukes, J. Beete (Joseph Beete), 1811-1869
    New Ross, A.L.S. 7p.and end. Concerning geology.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, [bart.], London, April 28, 1856; 7x4-1/2; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
    A.L.S. 7p.and add.,end. Concerning geology and volcanic craters.
  - Letter to Miss Holland, [May, 1856]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    Scope ad Contents note
    Darwin reports that an entomologist [T.V. Wollaston]staying with him said that the pupa Miss Holland had sent him would turn into a lackey moth.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, London, May 5, 1856; 7-1/2x5; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 3p. (see Lyell album C) Friendly letter. Natural history. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, Aug. 2, 1856; 5" x 8"; Fleming, John, 1785-1857
    Leith, A.L.S. 4p. Marriage of Andrew. Comments on Lyell's paper"On the successive changes on the temple of Serapis." Calls attention to error in 1855 ed. of the Manual.
  - Letter to Leonard Horner, Sept., 1856; 9x5-1/2; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Berlin, A.L.S. 1p. and end. In French. (see Lyell album, C) Friendly note. Concerning Dr. George Tilgman (?). Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to [Robert Monsey Rolfe], Lord Cranworth, Nov. 10, [1856?]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    Down, Bromley, Kent, A.L.S. 3p. Thanks for money for Down charities. Refuses invitation for Saturday due to health.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, Dec. 3, 1856; 4 1/2" x 7"; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    British Museum, A.L.S. 4p. Identification of fossil specimens.
  - Letter to [Charles Robert Darwin], Dec. 29, 1856; Davidson, Tho[mas William St. Clair]; 1817-1885.
    Brighton, Xerox of A.L.S. 4p. Brachiopods. Publications, including one of Darwin's for a French correspondent. Presented by Sydney Smith; 1976.
  - Letter to Sir Charles [Lyell], January 7, 1857; 4 1/2" x 7"; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    British Museum, A.L.S. 4p. Identification of specimens sent by Mr. W.R. Brodie.
  - Letter to Sir Cha[rle]s Lyell, [bart.], Jan. 8, 1857; 7x4-1/4; Falconer, Hugh, 1808-1865
    A.L.S. with initials. 1 p. and add. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, Jan. 27, 1857; 4 1/2" x 7"; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    British Museum, A.L.S. 4p. Identification of fossil specimen.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, Feb. 4, 1857; 4 1/2" x 7"; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    British Museum, A.L.S. 8p. Comparative ages of certain tertiary mammals found in England.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, Feb. 17, 1857; 4 1/2" x 7"; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    British Museum, A.L.S. 4p. Dr. Murchison's illness. Regrets that a fee is to be charged for his lectures. His misgivings about Coryphodon have been set at rest.
  - Letter to Mrs. [K.M.H.] Lyell, March 12, 1857; 6x4; Babington, Churchill, 1821-1889
    Suffolk, A.L.S. 3p. (see Lyell album, C) Praises her book highly. Refers to Hooker. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Sir Charles [Lyell], April 23, 1857; 4 1/2" x 7"; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    British Museum, A.L.S. 2p. Mammalian fossils from Purbeck. Publication of his "Lectures on Fossil Mammalia."
  - Letter to Sir Charles [Lyell] British Museum, April 25, 1857; 4 1/2" x 7"; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    A.L.S. 2p. Assures him there will be plenty of space for the Purbeck mammals in his work on fossil mammals.
  - Letter to Sir Charles [Lyell], April 30, 1857; 4 1/2" x 7"; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    British Museum, A.L.S. 4p. Still desires to offer his descriptions of the mammalia of Purbeck to the council of the Paleontographical Society. Is indebted to Sir Charles for his part in their discovery. His work on the History of British Fossil Reptiles.
  - Letter to [Charles] Lyell, Oct. 17, Nov. 15, 1857; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Bunbury, Charles James Fox, Sir, 1809-1885
    Mildenhall, A.L. 4p. (see Lyell album, C) Friendly letter. Botany. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, Feb. 4, 1858; 4 1/2" x 7"; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    British Museum, A.L.S. 3p. Desires a certain reference about the genus Placodus.
  - Letter to Sir Cha[rle]s Lyell,[bart.], London, April 3, 1858; 7x4-1/2; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
    A.L.S. 16p.and add.,end. Concerning volcanoes. Refers to Humboldt.
  - Letter to Sir Cha[rle]s Lyell, [bart.], May 8, 1858; 7x4-1/2; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
  - Letter to Mrs. [Lloyd] Horner, June 10, 1858; 7x4-1/2; Boott, Francis, 1792-1863
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Lyell album,C) Death of Robert Brown. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, [bart.], June 10, 1858; 7x4-1/2; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
    A.L.S. 8p. Concerning lava and volcano craters.
  - Letter to [Col. Poole], October 13 [1858]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    Down, Bromley, Kent, A.L.S. 4pp. Darwin reports that he has received a communication from Col. R. Curtis in India on the crowns and stripes of native horses, a subject in which he is particularly interested. Sends list of questions [not appended.]
  - Letter to Sir Charles [Lyell, bart.], Feb. 4, 1859; 7x4-1/2; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
    A.L.S. 4p. Concerning Elie de Beaumont on Etna. Refers to Humboldt and von Buch.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, [bart.], Feb. 7, 1859; 7x4-1/4; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
    A.L.S. 7p.and add.,end. Concerning volcanoes.
  - Letter to Dame Pertz, Feb. 14, 1859; 9x5-1/2; Ehrenberg, Christian Gottfried, 1795-1876
    Berlin, A.L.S. 2p. In German. (see Lyell album, C)
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, [bart.], London, May 12, 1859; 7x4-1/4; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
    A.L.S. 4p.and add.,end. Concerning volcanoes. Refers to Élie de Beaumont, Humboldt, von Buch, and Murchison.
  - Sketch of a fossil, May 13, 1859; 5-1/2x9; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    D. 1p., end. (see Lyell album, C), Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Sir Charles[ Lyell], June 4, 1859; 4 1/2" x 7"; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    British Museum, A.L.S. 1p. Vertebrae found in the Cambridge green-sand beds.
  - Letter to Mrs. [K.M.H.] Lyell, June 13, 1859; 6x3-1/2; Hooker, Joseph Dalton, Sir, 1817-1911
    Kew, A.L.S. 4p. (see Lyell album, C) Friendly letter. Botany. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, July 25, 1859; 7x4-1/2; Newton, Alfred, 1829-1907
    A.L.S. 8p., add., end. (see Lyell album. C) Geology of Scandinavia, Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Sir Cha[rle]s Lyell, June 26, 1859; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    A.L.S. 1p. and enc. - 12p., and env., end. Progressive development. Thinks transmutation may take place without transition. Listed in Apes,Angels,Victorians as June 25,1853.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell,[bart.], Sept. 4, 1859; 7x4-1/2; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, [bart.], Oct. 12, 1859; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 6p. Concerning the question of the geological age of sandstone.
  - Letter to Sir Cha[rle]s Lyell, Oct. 18, 1859; 4 1/2" x 7"; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    Jermyn St., A.L.S. 4p. and env., end. The Elgin beds.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, [bart.], Oct. 19, 1859; 7x4-1/2; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 12p. Concerning the geological formation of sandstone. Concerning fossils.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, 31 Oct., [1859]; 6 1/2" x 8 1/4"; Darwin, Charles,1809-1882.
    Wells Seneca, Monday (?) A.L.S. 4p. Printed: More letters of C. Darwin, v.127. B D25.L no. 175
  - Letter to F.J. Pictet de la Rive, [1859] Nov. 11; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    Darwin writes that he is sending a copy of the Origin; "it may possibly lead you to reflect further on the side opposed to your view".
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, [bart.], Nov. 17, 18[59?]; 7x4-1/2; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
    A.L.S. 7p. Concerning fossil man. Concerning volcanoes. Refers to Babbage.
  - Letter to Sir Cha[rle]s Lyell, [bart.], London, Dec. 12, 1859; 7x4-1/2; Scrope, George Poulett, 1797-1876
    A.L.S. 6p.and add.,end. Concerning geology and volcanoes. Refers to Humboldt.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, 22 Dec., [1859]; 4 3/4" x 7 1/2"; Darwin, Charles,1809-1882.
    Down, Bromley, Kent, A.L.S. 4p. Printed almost entirely: Life and letters of C. Darwin, v.2,245. B D25.L no. 186
  - Letter to [F.J. Pictet de la Rive], [1859] December 24; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    Darwin states that, "I rest my conviction solely on the fact, as it seems to me, that the theory explains large classes of facts otherwise inexplicable."
  - Letter to [Francis] Boott, Jan. 16, 1860; 8x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. (see Lyell album,C) Concerning Darwin's book. Agassiz is against it and he wished he could "shut Agassiz' mouth." Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to "Dear Sir", 16 Jan., [1860]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    Down, Bromley, Kent, A.L.S. 1p.and end. Requests works by Tennent on Ceylon, Owen on mammal distribution. Will pay whole account on receipt.
  - Letter to Lady [Mary Horner] Lyell, Jan. 26, 1860; 7x4-1/2; Boott, Francis, 1792-1863
    A.L.S. 4p. (see Lyell album, C) Concerning John Brown. Mentions Sir Charles. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Lady [Mary Horner] Lyell, Feb. 6, 1860; 7x4-1/2; Boott, Francis, 1792-1863
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Lyell album,C) Concerning John Brown. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir;", Feb. 6, [1860]; Darwin, Charles [Robert], 1809-1882.
    Down, Bromley, Kent, L.S. 4p. Geological observations. Glad he is to "give a little more age to the world."
  - Letter to "Dear Sir", [1860] Feruary 23; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    Darwin discusses the reception of his book [Origin]. He mentions the opinions of Asa Gray and Louis Agassiz.
  - Letter to Lady [Mary Horner] Lyell, March 12, 1860; 7x4-1/2; Boott, Francis, 1792-1863
    A.L.S. 3p. (see Lyell album C) Friendly letter. Mentions Darwin and Sir Charles. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to [Charles] Lyell, March 16, 1860; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Henslow, J. S. (John Stevens), 1796-1861
    Suffolk, A.L.S. 6p. (see Lyell album, C) Friendly letter. Mentions Darwin and Agassiz. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, March 17, [1860?]; 4 1/2" x 7"; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    Saturday morning. A.L. 4p. and env., end. il. Education of women.
  - Letter to Maxwell Masters, 21 March [1860-61]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
  - Letter to Miss Holland, [April, 1860]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
  - Letter to "Dear Sir", [1860] April 1; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    Darwin thanks the correspondent for his review of the Origin.
  - C[harles Robert] Darwin to, [13 May, 1860]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    A.L.S. 1p.and end. Requests publications.
  - Letter to [Jeffries Wyman], Oct. 3, [1860]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    Down, Bromley, Kent, Photostat of A.L.S. 10p. Printed: Isis, v.42,pt.2,1951,105-107. Presented by A.H. Dupree, Feb.1953. from originals in possession of Jeffries Wyman, Jr. Formerly in MISC MS COLLECTION, B D25.106
  - Letter to [Charles] Lyell, Oct. 7, 1860; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Henslow, J. S. (John Stevens), 1796-1861
    Ipswich, A.L.S. 12p. (see Lyell album, C) Geology of northern France. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to ----, Nov. 26, 1860; 7x4-1/2; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    A.L.S. 4p. (see Lyell album, C) Concerning craniums. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Mrs. [K.M.H.] Lyell, Nov. 27, 1860; 7x4-1/2; Boott, Francis, 1792-1863
    A.L.S. 4p. (see Lyell album, C) Botany. Friendly letter. Mentions Charles Lyell. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to [Jeffries Wyman], Dec. 3, [1860]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    Down, Bromley, Kent; Photostat of A.L.S. 4p. Printed: Isis, v.42,pt.2,1951,107-108. Presented by A.H. Dupree, Feb. 1953, From originals in possession of Jeffries Wyman, jr. Formerly in MISC MS COLLECTION, B. D25.107
  - Letter to Mrs.[K.M.H.] Lyell, Dec. 12, 1860; 7x4-1/2; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    A.L.S. 4p. (see Lyell album, C) Friendly letter. Concerning the birth of his son. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Mrs. [K.M.H.] Lyell, Dec. 18, 1860; 7x4-1/2; Boott, Francis, 1792-1863
    A.L.S. 3p. (see Lyell album,C) Friendly letter. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, 1860; 7x4-1/2; Wallace, Alfred Russel, 1823-1913
    London, Monday afternoon [ca.?]. A.L.S. 2p. (see Lyell album, C) Will call to discuss Darwin's work. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Dear Sir [Librarian], [1861] 7 January; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    Darwin orders a journal volume [Memoires presentee par divers savans a [Academie des Sciences] from a librarian.
  - Letter to "Dear Sir;", 8 Jan., [1861-1869]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    A.L.S. 1p. Acknowledgements. Comments on his health.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, [bart.] 61, Jan. 21, 1861; 7x4-1/2; Busk, George, 1807-1886
    A.L.S. 5P.and add.,end. Concerning the ethnology of the Baltic area.
  - Letter to [William?] Buckland, 1 Feb., [1861-1869]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    A.L.S. 4p. "Variation under domestication" restricted in scope. Discusses interbreeding; looks for London meeting; Darwin's health.
  - Letter to [Jeffries Wyman, Feb. 3, [1861]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    Down, Bromley Kent, Photostat of A.L.S. 4p. Printed: Isis, v.42, pt.2, 1951, 108-109. Presented by A.H. Dupree, Feb. 1953, from originals in possession of Jeffries Wyman, jr. Formerly B D25.108.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir;", 12 Feb., [1861-1869]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    L.S. 4p.end. & autograph p.s. Inquires about sex retios in fish, mammals & birds. Land & Water (Magazine).
  - Letter to "My dear Sir", 12 Feb., [1861-1869]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    A.L.S. 3p. Note to engraver; asks for bill; London "disagrees with my health." Mentions Geographical Society.
  - Letter to [Leonard Horner], 14 Feb., [1861]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    Down, A.L.S. 3p. Variations in nature arise from unknown causes, and are preserved by natural selection if beneficial. Gift of Owen & Miriam Gingerich in memory of Cecilia Payne Gaposchkin.
  - Ch[arles Robert] Darwin to, 29 February [1861-1869]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
  - Letter to "My dear Sir;", 29 Feb., [1861-1869]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    A.L.S. 2p. Experiments on plant fertilization. Thanks for presents, one "charlatanry." Mr. Busk, article by Thury.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, [bart.], April 17, 1861; 7x4-1/2; Busk, George, 1807-1886
    A.L.S. 7p.and add.,end.and sketch of a jawbone. Concerning fossils.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, [bart.], April 17, 1861; 7x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
  - Flowers picked at Humboldt's grave at Tegal, May, 1861; 9x5-1/2; Lyell, Katharine Murray (Horner), Mrs., d. 1915
    D. 1p. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir;", 7 May, [1861-1869]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    A.L.S.partly in Darwin's hand. 6p.with 2p. enclosures. Thanks for letters. Diverse points of ornithology and botany. Encloses queries; mentions Henslow.
  - Letter to Mrs. [K.M.H.] Lyell, June 15, 1861; 5-1/2x3-1/2; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    A.L.S. 4p. (see Lyell album, C) Friendly letter. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to "Dear Sir;", 20 June, [1861-1869]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    A.L.S. 2p.,end. Sends copy of paper "written many years ago" and not for publication; mentions Wallace's paper as "excellent."
  - Ch[arles Robert] Darwin to, 20 June [1861-1869]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, June 26, 1861; 4 1/2" x 7"; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    A.L.S. 4p. and env., end. Capacity of brain and convolutions in man and highest apes.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, July 20, [1861]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    2, Hesketh Crescent, Torquay, A.L.S. 4p. Portion printed: Life and letters of C. Darwin, v.2, 376. Formerly B D25.L no.258
  - Letter to "My dear Sir;", 24 July, [1861-1864]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    A.L.S. 4p. His son's illness, more on peloria; mentions Prosper Lucas, Botanical Society.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, [bart.], July 30, 1861; 9x7-1/4; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 2p. Friendly letter. Refers to Geikie.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, [bart.], Aug. 23, 1861; 7x4-1/2; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 7p. Friendly letter. Concerning geology. Refers to Humboldt.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles] Lyell, [bart.], Sept. 25, 1861; 7x4-1/2; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Norfolk, A.L.S. 4p.and add.,end. Friendly letter. Concerning geology. Refers to Scrope.
  - Letter to "Dear Sir;", 11 Oct., [1861-1869]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    L.S. 2p.,end. Thanks for book on language; health may prevent its being read.
  - Addressed envelope:, Oct. 17, 1861; 2-3/4x4-3/4; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    Mrs. [Lady Mary Horner] Lyell; A.D. 1p. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to "M. le baron" [Sir Charles Lyell], [1861 November 16?]; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, Nov. 28, 1861; 4 1/2" x 7"; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    Jermyn St., A.L.S. 3p. and env., end. Newark human skull.
  - Letter to Sir Charles [Lyell], Dec. 5, 1861; 7x4-1/2; Busk, George, 1807-1886
    Cavendish Square, A.L.S. 4p. (see Lyell album, C) Concerning a fossil skull. Formerly B D25.L1.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, Dec. 6, 1861; 4 1/2" x 7"; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    Jermyn St., A.L.S. 4p. and env., end. Is writing a review of St. Hilaire's "Trois Regnes." Cariano de Prado (?) elected to membership in ----. Desires to know what Lady Lyell thinks of the San Jacinto business.
  - Letter to "Dear Sir;" [ J.X.R. Caspary], 26 Dec., [1861-1869]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
    A.L.S. 3p.and end. Letter of thanks concerning crossing and fertilizing plants. Mentions Hooker.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, Jan. 25, 1862; 4 1/2" x 7"; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    Jermyn St. A.L.S. 4p. and env., end. Neanderthal skull. Pressure of work.
  - Letter to Charles [Robert] Darwin, Jan. 30, [1862?]; Murray, John (III), 1808-1892.
    A.L.S. 3p. Thanks for introduction to H. W. Bates and wishes to see his manuscript for publication.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, March 10, 1862; 4 1/2" x 7"; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    London, A.L.S. 4p.and env., end. Ramsay's glacial theory of lakes of Switzerland.
  - Letter to Sir Charles Lyell, [bart.], April 21, 1862; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Rolleston, George, 1829-1881
    Oxford, A.L.in 3rd.P. 3p.and add.,end. Concerning hibernation.